<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<section id="greece" title="Greece">
   <section title="Introduction">
      <section title="Background">Greece achieved independence from the Ottoman Empire in 1830. During the second half of the 19th century and the first half of the 20th century, it gradually added neighboring islands and territories, most with Greek-speaking populations. In World War II, Greece was first invaded by Italy (1940) and subsequently occupied by Germany (1941-44); fighting endured in a protracted civil war between supporters of the king and other anti-communist and communist rebels. Following the latter's defeat in 1949, Greece joined NATO in 1952. In 1967, a group of military officers seized power, establishing a military dictatorship that suspended many political liberties and forced the king to flee the country. In 1974 following the collapse of the dictatorship, democratic elections and a referendum created a parliamentary republic and abolished the monarchy. In 1981, Greece joined the EC (now the EU); it became the 12th member of the European Economic and Monetary Union (EMU) in 2001. Greece has suffered a severe economic crisis since late 2009, due to nearly a decade of chronic overspending and structural rigidities. Beginning in 2010, Greece entered three bailout agreements - with the European Commission, the European Central Bank (ECB), the IMF, and the third in 2015 with the European Stability Mechanism (ESM) - worth in total about $300 billion. The Greek Government formally exited the third bailout in August 2018.</section>
   </section>
   <section title="Geography">
      <section title="Location">Southern Europe, bordering the Aegean Sea, Ionian Sea, and the Mediterranean Sea, between Albania and Turkey</section>
      <geographic_coordinates>
         <latitude/>
         <longitude/>
      </geographic_coordinates>
      <map_references>Europe</map_references>
      <area>
         <total>131957 sq km</total>
         <land>130647 sq km</land>
         <water>1310 sq km</water>
         <comparative>slightly smaller than Alabama</comparative> (Global rank: 98)</area>
      <land_boundaries>
         <total>1110 km</total>
         <border_countries>
            <country>Albania</country>
            <border_length>212 km</border_length>
         </border_countries>
         <border_countries>
            <country>Bulgaria</country>
            <border_length>472 km</border_length>
         </border_countries>
         <border_countries>
            <country>Macedonia</country>
            <border_length>234 km</border_length>
         </border_countries>
         <border_countries>
            <country>Turkey</country>
            <border_length>192 km</border_length>
         </border_countries>
      </land_boundaries>
      <coastline>13676 km</coastline>
      <maritime_claims>
         <territorial_sea>12 nm</territorial_sea>
         <continental_shelf>200 m</continental_shelf>
      </maritime_claims>
      <climate>temperate; mild, wet winters; hot, dry summers</climate>
      <terrain>mountainous with ranges extending into the sea as peninsulas or chains of islands</terrain>
      <elevation>
         <mean_elevation>498 m</mean_elevation>
         <lowest_point>
            <name>Mediterranean Sea</name>
            <elevation>0 m</elevation>
         </lowest_point>
         <highest_point>
            <name>Mount Olympus</name>
            <elevation>
               <value>2917</value>
            </elevation>
         </highest_point>
      </elevation>
      <natural_resources>
         <resources>lignite</resources>
         <resources>petroleum</resources>
         <resources>iron ore</resources>
         <resources>bauxite</resources>
         <resources>lead</resources>
         <resources>zinc</resources>
         <resources>nickel</resources>
         <resources>magnesite</resources>
         <resources>marble</resources>
         <resources>salt</resources>
         <resources>hydropower potential</resources>
      </natural_resources>
      <land_use>
         <by_sector>
            <agricultural_land_total>63.4 %</agricultural_land_total>
            <arable_land>19.7 %</arable_land>
            <permanent_crops>8.9 %</permanent_crops>
            <permanent_pasture>34.8 %</permanent_pasture>
            <forest>30.5 %</forest>
            <other>6.1 %</other>
         </by_sector> [2011]</land_use>
      <irrigated_land>15550 sq km [2012]</irrigated_land>
      <population_distribution>one-third of the population lives in and around metropolitan Athens; the remainder of the country has moderate population density mixed with sizeable urban clusters</population_distribution>
      <natural_hazards>
         <description>severe earthquakes</description>
         <type>hazard</type>
      </natural_hazards>
      <natural_hazards>
         <description>Santorini (367 m) has been deemed a Decade Volcano by the International Association of Volcanology and Chemistry of the Earth's Interior, worthy of study due to its explosive history and close proximity to human populations; although there have been very few eruptions in recent centuries, Methana and Nisyros in the Aegean are classified as historically active</description>
         <type>volcanism</type>
      </natural_hazards>
      <environment>
         <current_issues>air pollution</current_issues>
         <current_issues>air emissions from transport and electricity power stations</current_issues>
         <current_issues>water pollution</current_issues>
         <current_issues>degradation of coastal zones</current_issues>
         <current_issues>loss of biodiversity in terrestrial and marine ecosystems</current_issues>
         <current_issues>increasing municipal and industrial waste</current_issues>
         <international_agreements>
            <party_to>Air Pollution</party_to>
            <party_to>Air Pollution-Nitrogen Oxides</party_to>
            <party_to>Air Pollution-Sulfur 94</party_to>
            <party_to>Antarctic-Environmental Protocol</party_to>
            <party_to>Antarctic-Marine Living Resources</party_to>
            <party_to>Antarctic Treaty</party_to>
            <party_to>Biodiversity</party_to>
            <party_to>Climate Change</party_to>
            <party_to>Climate Change-Kyoto Protocol</party_to>
            <party_to>Desertification</party_to>
            <party_to>Endangered Species</party_to>
            <party_to>Environmental Modification</party_to>
            <party_to>Hazardous Wastes</party_to>
            <party_to>Law of the Sea</party_to>
            <party_to>Marine Dumping</party_to>
            <party_to>Ozone Layer Protection</party_to>
            <party_to>Ship Pollution</party_to>
            <party_to>Tropical Timber 83</party_to>
            <party_to>Tropical Timber 94</party_to>
            <party_to>Wetlands</party_to>
            <signed_but_not_ratified>Air Pollution-Persistent Organic Pollutants</signed_but_not_ratified>
            <signed_but_not_ratified>Air Pollution-Volatile Organic Compounds</signed_but_not_ratified>
         </international_agreements>
      </environment>
   </section>
   <section title="People">
      <population>10607051 (Global rank: 86) [2020-07-01]</population>
      <nationality>
         <noun>Greek(s)</noun>
         <adjective>Greek</adjective>
      </nationality>
      <ethnic_groups>
         <ethnicity>91.6 %</ethnicity>
         <ethnicity>4.4 %</ethnicity>
         <ethnicity>4 %</ethnicity> [2011]</ethnic_groups>
      <languages>
         <language>99 %</language>
         <language>1 %</language>
      </languages>
      <religions>
         <religion>
            <name>Greek Orthodox</name>
         </religion> [2015]</religions>
      <dependency_ratios>
         <ratios>
            <total_dependency_ratio>56.1 %</total_dependency_ratio>
            <youth_dependency_ratio>21.3 %</youth_dependency_ratio>
            <elderly_dependency_ratio>34.8 %</elderly_dependency_ratio>
            <potential_support_ratio>2.9 %</potential_support_ratio>
         </ratios> [2020]</dependency_ratios>
      <median_age>
         <total>45.3 years</total>
         <male>43.7 years</male>
         <female>46.8 years</female> (Global rank: 9) [2020]</median_age>
      <population_growth_rate>-0.31 (Global rank: 220) [2020]</population_growth_rate>
      <birth_rate>7.8 births per 1000 population (Global rank: 225) [2020]</birth_rate>
      <death_rate>12 deaths per 1000 population (Global rank: 17) [2020]</death_rate>
      <net_migration_rate>0.9 migrants per 1000 population (Global rank: 61) [2020]</net_migration_rate>
      <population_distribution>one-third of the population lives in and around metropolitan Athens; the remainder of the country has moderate population density mixed with sizeable urban clusters</population_distribution>
      <urbanization>
         <urban_population>79.7 % [2020]</urban_population>
         <rate_of_urbanization>0.22 %</rate_of_urbanization>
         <total_population_growth_rate_v._urban_population_growth_rate_2000_2030>PDF</total_population_growth_rate_v._urban_population_growth_rate_2000_2030>
      </urbanization>
      <major_urban_areas>
         <places>Athens</places>
         <places>Thessaloniki</places> [2020]</major_urban_areas>
      <mothers_mean_age_at_first_birth>29.9</mothers_mean_age_at_first_birth>
      <maternal_mortality_rate>3 deaths per 100k live births (Global rank: 178) [2017]</maternal_mortality_rate>
      <infant_mortality_rate>
         <total>3.7 deaths per 1000 live births</total>
         <male>4 deaths per 1000 live births</male>
         <female>3.3 deaths per 1000 live births</female> (Global rank: 194) [2020]</infant_mortality_rate>
      <life_expectancy_at_birth>
         <total_population>81.1 years</total_population>
         <male>78.5 years</male>
         <female>83.8 years</female> (Global rank: 38) [2020]</life_expectancy_at_birth>
      <total_fertility_rate>1.38 children born per woman (Global rank: 217) [2020]</total_fertility_rate>
      <physicians_density>5.48 physicians per 1000 population [2017]</physicians_density>
      <hospital_bed_density>4.2 beds per 1000 population [2017]</hospital_bed_density>
      <drinking_water_source>
         <improved>
            <urban>100 percent of population</urban>
            <rural>100 percent of population</rural>
            <total>100 percent of population</total>
         </improved>
         <unimproved>
            <urban>0 percent of population</urban>
            <rural>0 percent of population</rural>
            <total>0 percent of population</total>
         </unimproved> [2017]</drinking_water_source>
      <sanitation_facility_access>
         <improved>
            <urban>100 percent of population</urban>
            <rural>100 percent of population</rural>
            <total>100 percent of population</total>
         </improved>
         <unimproved>
            <urban>0 percent of population</urban>
            <rural>0 percent of population</rural>
            <total>0 percent of population</total>
         </unimproved> [2017]</sanitation_facility_access>
      <hiv_aids>
         <adult_prevalence_rate>0.2 % of adults (Global rank: 97) [2017]</adult_prevalence_rate>
         <people_living_with_hiv_aids>14000 (Global rank: 93) [2017]</people_living_with_hiv_aids>
         <deaths>100 [2017]</deaths>
      </hiv_aids>
      <adult_obesity>24.9 % of adults (Global rank: 54) [2016]</adult_obesity>
      <literacy>
         <definition>age 15 and over can read and write</definition>
         <total_population>97.7 %</total_population>
         <male>98.5 %</male>
         <female>96.9 %</female> [2015]</literacy>
      <school_life_expectancy>
         <total>20 years</total>
         <male>20 years</male>
         <female>20 years</female> [2018]</school_life_expectancy>
      <youth_unemployment>
         <total>39.9 %</total>
         <male>36.4 %</male>
         <female>43.9 %</female> (Global rank: 11) [2018]</youth_unemployment>
   </section>
   <section title="International organization participation">
      <organization>Australia Group</organization>
      <organization>BIS</organization>
      <organization>BSEC</organization>
      <organization>CD</organization>
      <organization>CE</organization>
      <organization>CERN</organization>
      <organization>EAPC</organization>
      <organization>EBRD</organization>
      <organization>ECB</organization>
      <organization>EIB</organization>
      <organization>EMU</organization>
      <organization>ESA</organization>
      <organization>EU</organization>
      <organization>FAO</organization>
      <organization>FATF</organization>
      <organization>IAEA</organization>
      <organization>IBRD</organization>
      <organization>ICAO</organization>
      <organization>ICC </organization>
      <organization>ICCt</organization>
      <organization>ICRM</organization>
      <organization>IDA</organization>
      <organization>IEA</organization>
      <organization>IFAD</organization>
      <organization>IFC</organization>
      <organization>IFRCS</organization>
      <organization>IGAD </organization>
      <organization>IHO</organization>
      <organization>ILO</organization>
      <organization>IMF</organization>
      <organization>IMO</organization>
      <organization>IMSO</organization>
      <organization>Interpol</organization>
      <organization>IOC</organization>
      <organization>IOM</organization>
      <organization>IPU</organization>
      <organization>ISO</organization>
      <organization>ITSO</organization>
      <organization>ITU</organization>
      <organization>ITUC </organization>
      <organization>MIGA</organization>
      <organization>NATO</organization>
      <organization>NEA</organization>
      <organization>NSG</organization>
      <organization>OAS </organization>
      <organization>OECD</organization>
      <organization>OIF</organization>
      <organization>OPCW</organization>
      <organization>OSCE</organization>
      <organization>PCA</organization>
      <organization>Schengen Convention</organization>
      <organization>SELEC</organization>
      <organization>UN</organization>
      <organization>UNCTAD</organization>
      <organization>UNESCO</organization>
      <organization>UNHCR</organization>
      <organization>UNIDO</organization>
      <organization>UNIFIL</organization>
      <organization>UNWTO</organization>
      <organization>UPU</organization>
      <organization>WCO</organization>
      <organization>WFTU </organization>
      <organization>WHO</organization>
      <organization>WIPO</organization>
      <organization>WMO</organization>
      <organization>WTO</organization>
      <organization>ZC</organization>
   </section>
   <section title="Economy">
      <section title="Overview">Greece has a capitalist economy with a public sector accounting for about 40% of GDP and with per capita GDP about two-thirds that of the leading euro-zone economies. Tourism provides 18% of GDP. Immigrants make up nearly one-fifth of the work force, mainly in agricultural and unskilled jobs. Greece is a major beneficiary of EU aid, equal to about 3.3% of annual GDP.
The Greek economy averaged growth of about 4% per year between 2003 and 2007, but the economy went into recession in 2009 as a result of the world financial crisis, tightening credit conditions, and Athens' failure to address a growing budget deficit. By 2013, the economy had contracted 26%, compared with the pre-crisis level of 2007. Greece met the EU's Growth and Stability Pact budget deficit criterion of no more than 3% of GDP in 2007-08, but violated it in 2009, when the deficit reached 15% of GDP. Deteriorating public finances, inaccurate and misreported statistics, and consistent underperformance on reforms prompted major credit rating agencies to downgrade Greece's international debt rating in late 2009 and led the country into a financial crisis. Under intense pressure from the EU and international market participants, the government accepted a bailout program that called on Athens to cut government spending, decrease tax evasion, overhaul the civil-service, health-care, and pension systems, and reform the labor and product markets. Austerity measures reduced the deficit to 1.3% in 2017. Successive Greek governments, however, failed to push through many of the most unpopular reforms in the face of widespread political opposition, including from the country's powerful labor unions and the general public.
In April 2010, a leading credit agency assigned Greek debt its lowest possible credit rating, and in May 2010, the IMF and euro-zone governments provided Greece emergency short- and medium-term loans worth $147 billion so that the country could make debt repayments to creditors. Greece, however, struggled to meet the targets set by the EU and the IMF, especially after Eurostat - the EU's statistical office - revised upward Greece's deficit and debt numbers for 2009 and 2010. European leaders and the IMF agreed in October 2011 to provide Athens a second bailout package of $169 billion. The second deal called for holders of Greek government bonds to write down a significant portion of their holdings to try to alleviate Greece’s government debt burden. However, Greek banks, saddled with a significant portion of sovereign debt, were adversely affected by the write down and $60 billion of the second bailout package was set aside to ensure the banking system was adequately capitalized.
In 2014, the Greek economy began to turn the corner on the recession. Greece achieved three significant milestones: balancing the budget - not including debt repayments; issuing government debt in financial markets for the first time since 2010; and generating 0.7% GDP growth — the first economic expansion since 2007.
Despite the nascent recovery, widespread discontent with austerity measures helped propel the far-left Coalition of the Radical Left (SYRIZA) party into government in national legislative elections in January 2015. Between January and July 2015, frustrations grew between the SYRIZA-led government and Greece’s EU and IMF creditors over the implementation of bailout measures and disbursement of funds. The Greek government began running up significant arrears to suppliers, while Greek banks relied on emergency lending, and Greece’s future in the euro zone was called into question. To stave off a collapse of the banking system, Greece imposed capital controls in June 2015, then became the first developed nation to miss a loan payment to the IMF, rattling international financial markets. Unable to reach an agreement with creditors, Prime Minister Alexios TSIPRAS held a nationwide referendum on 5 July on whether to accept the terms of Greece’s bailout, campaigning for the ultimately successful "no" vote. The TSIPRAS government subsequently agreed, however, to a new $96 billion bailout in order to avert Greece’s exit from the monetary bloc. On 20 August 2015, Greece signed its third bailout, allowing it to cover significant debt payments to its EU and IMF creditors and to ensure the banking sector retained access to emergency liquidity. The TSIPRAS government — which retook office on 20 September 2015 after calling new elections in late August — successfully secured disbursal of two delayed tranches of bailout funds. Despite the economic turmoil, Greek GDP did not contract as sharply as feared, boosted in part by a strong tourist season.
In 2017, Greece saw improvements in GDP and unemployment. Unfinished economic reforms, a massive non-performing loan problem, and ongoing uncertainty regarding the political direction of the country hold the economy back. Some estimates put Greece’s black market at 20- to 25% of GDP, as more people have stopped reporting their income to avoid paying taxes that, in some cases, have risen to 70% of an individual’s gross income.</section>
      <gdp>
         <purchasing_power_parity>
            <annual_values>299300000000 USD [2017]</annual_values>
            <annual_values>295300000000 USD [2016]</annual_values>
            <annual_values>296000000000 USD [2015]</annual_values> (Global rank: 56)</purchasing_power_parity>
         <official_exchange_rate>200700000000 $ [2017]</official_exchange_rate>
         <real_growth_rate>
            <annual_values>1.87 % [2019]</annual_values>
            <annual_values>1.91 % [2018]</annual_values>
            <annual_values>1.44 % [2017]</annual_values> (Global rank: 145)</real_growth_rate>
         <per_capita_purchasing_power_parity>
            <annual_values>27800 USD [2017]</annual_values>
            <annual_values>27400 USD [2016]</annual_values>
            <annual_values>27300 USD [2015]</annual_values> (Global rank: 75)</per_capita_purchasing_power_parity>
         <composition>
            <by_end_use>
               <end_uses>
                  <household_consumption>69.6 %</household_consumption>
                  <government_consumption>20.1 %</government_consumption>
                  <investment_in_fixed_capital>12.5 %</investment_in_fixed_capital>
                  <investment_in_inventories>-1 %</investment_in_inventories>
                  <exports_of_goods_and_services>33.4 %</exports_of_goods_and_services>
                  <imports_of_goods_and_services>-34.7 %</imports_of_goods_and_services>
               </end_uses> [2017]</by_end_use>
            <by_sector_of_origin>
               <sectors>
                  <agriculture>4.1 %</agriculture>
                  <industry>16.9 %</industry>
                  <services>79.1 %</services>
               </sectors> [2017]</by_sector_of_origin>
         </composition>
      </gdp>
      <gross_national_saving>
         <annual_values>10.9 percent of gdp [2017]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>9.5 percent of gdp [2016]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>9.6 percent of gdp [2015]</annual_values> (Global rank: 159)</gross_national_saving>
      <agriculture_products>
         <products>wheat</products>
         <products>corn</products>
         <products>barley</products>
         <products>sugar beets</products>
         <products>olives</products>
         <products>tomatoes</products>
         <products>wine</products>
         <products>tobacco</products>
         <products>potatoes</products>
         <products>beef</products>
         <products>dairy products</products>
      </agriculture_products>
      <industries>
         <industries>tourism</industries>
         <industries>food</industries>
         <industries>tobacco processing</industries>
         <industries>textiles</industries>
         <industries>chemicals</industries>
         <industries>metal products</industries>
         <industries>mining</industries>
         <industries>petroleum</industries>
      </industries>
      <industrial_production_growth_rate>
         <annual_percentage_increase>3.5</annual_percentage_increase> (Global rank: 85) [2017]</industrial_production_growth_rate>
      <labor_force>
         <total_size>
            <total_people>4000000</total_people> (Global rank: 90) [2020]</total_size>
         <by_occupation>
            <occupation>
               <agriculture>12.6 %</agriculture>
               <industry>15 %</industry>
               <services>72.4 %</services>
            </occupation> [2015-10-30]</by_occupation>
      </labor_force>
      <unemployment_rate>
         <annual_values>17.3 % [2019]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>19.34 % [2018]</annual_values> (Global rank: 182)</unemployment_rate>
      <population_below_poverty_line>36 % [2014]</population_below_poverty_line>
      <household_income_by_percentage_share>
         <lowest_ten_percent>1.7 %</lowest_ten_percent>
         <highest_ten_percent>26.7 %</highest_ten_percent> [2015]</household_income_by_percentage_share>
      <budget>
         <revenues>97990000000 USD</revenues>
         <expenditures>96350000000 USD</expenditures> [2017]</budget>
      <taxes_and_other_revenues>48.8 % of gdp (Global rank: 17) [2017]</taxes_and_other_revenues>
      <budget_surplus_or_deficit>0.8 % of gdp (Global rank: 36) [2017]</budget_surplus_or_deficit>
      <public_debt>
         <annual_values>181.8 percent of gdp [2017]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>183.5 percent of gdp [2016]</annual_values> (Global rank: 2)</public_debt>
      <fiscal_year/>
      <inflation_rate>
         <annual_values>1.1 % [2017]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>0 % [2016]</annual_values> (Global rank: 59)</inflation_rate>
      <current_account_balance>
         <annual_values>-3114000000 USD [2019]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>-6245000000 USD [2018]</annual_values> (Global rank: 175)</current_account_balance>
      <exports>
         <total_value>
            <annual_values>31540000000 USD [2017]</annual_values>
            <annual_values>27100000000 USD [2016]</annual_values> (Global rank: 63)</total_value>
         <commodities>
            <by_commodity>food</by_commodity>
            <by_commodity>beverages</by_commodity>
            <by_commodity>manufactured goods</by_commodity>
            <by_commodity>petroleum products</by_commodity>
            <by_commodity>chemicals</by_commodity>
            <by_commodity>textiles</by_commodity>
         </commodities>
         <partners>
            <by_country>10.6 %</by_country>
            <by_country>7.1 %</by_country>
            <by_country>6.8 %</by_country>
            <by_country>6.5 %</by_country>
            <by_country>4.9 %</by_country>
            <by_country>4.3 %</by_country> [2017]</partners>
      </exports>
      <imports>
         <total_value>
            <annual_values>52270000000 USD [2017]</annual_values>
            <annual_values>45450000000 USD [2016]</annual_values> (Global rank: 52)</total_value>
         <commodities>
            <by_commodity>machinery</by_commodity>
            <by_commodity>transport equipment</by_commodity>
            <by_commodity>fuels</by_commodity>
            <by_commodity>chemicals</by_commodity>
         </commodities>
         <partners>
            <by_country>10.4 %</by_country>
            <by_country>8.2 %</by_country>
            <by_country>6.8 %</by_country>
            <by_country>6.3 %</by_country>
            <by_country>6.1 %</by_country>
            <by_country>5.4 %</by_country>
            <by_country>5.3 %</by_country>
            <by_country>4.3 %</by_country> [2017]</partners>
      </imports>
      <reserves_of_foreign_exchange_and_gold>
         <annual_values>7807000000 USD [2017-12-31]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>6026000000 USD [2015-12-31]</annual_values> (Global rank: 80)</reserves_of_foreign_exchange_and_gold>
      <external_debt>
         <annual_values>506600000000 USD [2016-03-31]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>468200000000 USD [2015-03-31]</annual_values> (Global rank: 23)</external_debt>
      <exchange_rates>
         <annual_values>0.885 USD [2017]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>0.903 USD [2016]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>0.9214 USD [2015]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>0.885 USD [2014]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>0.7634 USD [2013]</annual_values>
      </exchange_rates>
   </section>
   <section title="Energy">
      <section title="Electricity">
         <access>
            <total_electrification>100 %</total_electrification> [2020]</access>
         <production>52050000000 kWh (Global rank: 53) [2016]</production>
         <consumption>56890000000 kWh (Global rank: 45) [2016]</consumption>
         <exports>1036999999.9999999 kWh (Global rank: 58) [2016]</exports>
         <imports>9833000000 kWh (Global rank: 27) [2016]</imports>
         <installed_generating_capacity>19170000 kW (Global rank: 46) [2016]</installed_generating_capacity>
         <by_source>
            <fossil_fuels>57 (Global rank: 137) [2016]</fossil_fuels>
            <nuclear_fuels>0 (Global rank: 98) [2017]</nuclear_fuels>
            <hydroelectric_plants>14 (Global rank: 105) [2017]</hydroelectric_plants>
            <other_renewable_sources>29 (Global rank: 19) [2017]</other_renewable_sources>
         </by_source>
      </section>
      <section title="Crude oil">
         <production>4100 bbl per day (Global rank: 80) [2018]</production>
         <exports>3229 bbl per day (Global rank: 67) [2017]</exports>
         <imports>484300 bbl per day (Global rank: 20) [2017]</imports>
         <proved_reserves>10000000 bbl (Global rank: 90) [2018-01-01]</proved_reserves>
      </section>
      <section title="Refined petroleum products">
         <production>655400 bbl per day (Global rank: 28) [2017]</production>
         <consumption>304100 bbl per day (Global rank: 43) [2017]</consumption>
         <exports>371900 bbl per day (Global rank: 22) [2017]</exports>
         <imports>192200 bbl per day (Global rank: 35) [2017]</imports>
      </section>
      <natural_gas>
         <production>8000000 cubic metres (Global rank: 93) [2017]</production>
         <consumption>4927000000 cubic metres (Global rank: 61) [2017]</consumption>
         <exports>0 cubic metres (Global rank: 112) [2017]</exports>
         <imports>4984000000 cubic metres (Global rank: 36) [2017]</imports>
         <proved_reserves>991100000 cubic metres (Global rank: 100) [2018-01-01]</proved_reserves>
      </natural_gas>
      <carbon_dioxide_emissions_from_consumption_of_energy>69370000 megatonnes (Global rank: 51) [2017]</carbon_dioxide_emissions_from_consumption_of_energy>
   </section>
   <section title="Communications">
      <telephones>
         <fixed_lines>5080386 (Global rank: 29) [2019]</fixed_lines>
         <mobile_cellular>12070571 (Global rank: 75) [2019]</mobile_cellular>
      </telephones>
      <broadcast_media>broadcast media dominated by the private sector; roughly 150 private TV channels, about 10 of which broadcast nationwide; 1 government-owned terrestrial TV channel with national coverage; 3 privately owned satellite channels; multi-channel satellite and cable TV services available; upwards of 1,500 radio stations, all of them privately owned; government-owned broadcaster has 2 national radio stations</broadcast_media>
      <internet>
         <country_code>.gr</country_code>
         <users>7783381 (Global rank: 61) [2018-07-01]</users>
      </internet>
   </section>
   <section title="Transportation">
      <pipelines>
         <by_type>1329 km</by_type>
         <by_type>94 km</by_type> [2013]</pipelines>
      <railways>
         <total>2548 km</total>
         <standard_gauge>1565 km 1.435-m</standard_gauge>
         <narrow_gauge>961 km 1.000-m</narrow_gauge> (Global rank: 67) [2014]</railways>
      <roadways>
         <total>117000 km</total> (Global rank: 42) [2018]</roadways>
      <waterways>6 km [2012]</waterways>
      <merchant_marine>1308 (Global rank: 22) [2019]</merchant_marine>
      <ports_and_terminals>
         <major_seaports>Aspropyrgos</major_seaports>
         <major_seaports>Pachi</major_seaports>
         <major_seaports>Piraeus</major_seaports>
         <major_seaports>Thessaloniki</major_seaports>
         <oil_terminals>Agioi Theodoroi</oil_terminals>
         <container_ports>Piraeus</container_ports>
         <liquid_natural_gas_terminals_import>Revithoussa</liquid_natural_gas_terminals_import> [2017]</ports_and_terminals>
   </section>
   <section title="Military and security">
      <expenditures>
         <annual_values>2.28 percent of gdp [2019]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>2.48 percent of gdp [2018]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>2.34 percent of gdp [2017]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>2.38 percent of gdp [2016]</annual_values>
         <annual_values>2.3 percent of gdp [2015]</annual_values> (Global rank: 41)</expenditures>
      <service_age_and_obligation>19 years of age [2014]</service_age_and_obligation>
   </section>
   <section title="Transnational issues">
      <disputes>Greece and Turkey continue discussions to resolve their complex maritime, air, territorial, and boundary disputes in the Aegean Sea</disputes>
      <disputes>the mass migration of unemployed Albanians still remains a problem for developed countries, chiefly Greece and Italy</disputes>
      <refugees_and_iternally_displaced_persons>
         <refugees>
            <by_country>
               <section title="People">26696</section>
               <country_of_origin>Syria</country_of_origin>
            </by_country>
            <by_country>
               <section title="People">17685</section>
               <country_of_origin>Afghanistan</country_of_origin>
            </by_country>
            <by_country>
               <section title="People">9614</section>
               <country_of_origin>Afghanistan</country_of_origin>
            </by_country> [2019]</refugees>
         <stateless_persons>4734 [2019]</stateless_persons>
      </refugees_and_iternally_displaced_persons>
      <illicit_drugs/>
   </section>
</section>
